البياعة أو ورقان، قرية سورية جميلة، تتبع ناحية شران، منطقة
عفرين في ريف حلب الشمالي.
Al Bayya'a or Wirgan is a beautiful Syrian village belonging
to the Sharran sub-district, Afrin district in the northern
Aleppo countryside.
وهي تقع على بعد خمسة عشر كيلومتراً شمال شرق شران، وأيضاً على
بعد ثلاثين كيلومتراً شمال شرق عفرين.
It is located 15 kilometers northeast of Sharran, and also
30 kilometers northeast of Afrin.
وتبعد عن الحدود التركية ثلاثة كيلومترات باتجاه الغرب.
It is three kilometers away from the Turkish border to the
west.
وقد بنيت القرية على السفوح الأربعة لجبل متوسط الارتفاع.
The village was built on the four slopes of a medium-height
mountain.
من أشهر معالمها وادي جهنم جنوب القرية، والذي يفصلها عن قرية
عين علو في الجنوب أيضاً.
Among its most famous landmarks is the Valley of Hell south
of the village, which separates it from the village of Ain
Alo to the south as well.
وأيضاً نبعة الضيعة كما يسمونها هنا، والتي تقع أيضاً في
جنوبها.
And also the village spring, as they call it here, which is
also located to its south.
البياعة توجد في منطقة تغص بالآثار التاريخية.
Al Bayya'a is located in an area full of historical ruins.
وخاصة الجسور الموجودة في قرية عرب ويران، والجسور الرومانية
الموجودة في دير صوان.
Especially the bridges in the village of Arab Wiran, and the
Roman bridges in Deir Sawwan.
إضافة إلى قلعة النبي هوري التي تبعد عن القرية اثني عشر
كيلومتراً باتجاه الشمال.
In addition to the Nebi Houri Citadel, which is 12
kilometers away from the village to the north.
يعتمد أهلها على الزراعة وخاصة زراعة الزيتون والرمان والكرمة.
Its people rely on agriculture, especially the cultivation
of olives, pomegranates, and vines.
وعلى تربية الماعز والأغنام.
And on raising goats and sheep.
يشكل أهالي القرية فسيفساء سورية متميزة من الأكراد والعرب
والتركمان.
The people of the village form a distinct Syrian mosaic of
Kurds, Arabs, and Turkmen.
ورغم وجود مدرسة ابتدائية في القرية، إلا أن نسبة التعليم فيها
متدنية.
Despite the presence of a primary school in the village, the
education rate there is low.
بسبب نمط الحياة المعتمد على الزراعة وتربية الحيوانات.
Due to the lifestyle that relies on agriculture and animal
husbandry.
ورقان أو البياعة، ورغم وجودها في منطقة تزدحم فيها الآثار
الرومانية والحثية.
Wirgan or Al Bayya'a, despite its location in an area
crowded with Roman and Hittite ruins.
إلا أن وجودها الحقيقي ربما لا يعود إلى أكثر من منتصف الفترة
العثمانية.
Its true existence might not date back further than the
middle of the Ottoman period.
والقرية الحالية وسكانها الحاليين ربما لا يزيد عمرهم عن مئة
سنة على أكثر تقدير.
And the current village and its current inhabitants probably
are not older than a hundred years at most.
للحديث عن تاريخ قرية ورقان أو البياعة، يسرنا أن يكون ضيفاً
معنا..
To talk about the history of the village of Wirgan or Al
Bayya'a, we are pleased to have as our guest...
العم محمود عبدو، أحد أكبر الرجال المعمرين في هذه القرية
والمهتم بتاريخها.
Uncle Mahmoud Abdo, one of the oldest men in this village
and someone interested in its history.
الله يعطيك العافية عمي محمود.
May God give you health, Uncle Mahmoud.
الله يعافيك أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God give you health, welcome.
احكي لي شوي، باعتبارك إنت مهتم بالتاريخ فعلاً.
Tell me a little bit, considering you are genuinely
interested in history.
يعني وجود ورقان هون، بهي المنطقة هي بالذات، شو أهميته؟
I mean, the existence of Wirgan here, in this particular
area, what is its significance?
يعني أنا متل ما بعرف نحن شرقنا، شرق جنوب موجود جسر فرنسي..
I mean, as I know, to our east, east-south there is a French
bridge...
جسر عرب ويران.
The Arab Wiran bridge.
عرب ويران؟
Arab Wiran?
أيوه.
Yes.
وأيضاً شمالينا في..
And also to our north there is...
شمالينا جسر على نهر عفرين، جسر روماني.
To our north, a bridge on the Afrin River, a Roman bridge.
جسر روماني تبع دير صوان.
The Roman bridge of Deir Sawwan.
دير صوان، وجسر التاني الروماني على نهر صابون.
Deir Sawwan, and the other Roman bridge is on the Saboun
River.
تمام، وعنا قريب من هون قلعة النبي هوري.
Right, and near here we have the Nebi Houri Citadel.
قلعة النبي هوري شماليتنا.
The Nebi Houri Citadel is to our north.
إيوه، ونهر عفرين بيمر غربيتنا.
Yes, and the Afrin River passes to our west.
هذا نهر عفرين من هون، هي البحيرة.
This is the Afrin River right here, this lake.
طيب، وجنوبي...
Okay, and to the south...
جنوبي القرية فيها وادي جهنم.
South of the village there is the Valley of Hell.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
كل هاد الكلام..
All of this talk...
نعم.
Yes.
خلى الإنسان يستوطن هون؟
Made people settle here?
نعم، الإنسان الأولي..
Yes, the early humans...
ما كان يستثمروا الأراضي زيادة.
Did not utilize the lands much.
فلذلك وين كان ينوجد الماء..
Therefore, wherever water was found...
يسكنون عند الماء لسقي مواشيهم.
They would live near the water to water their livestock.
نعم.
Yes.
هون النبع، وهون النبع.
Here is a spring, and here is a spring.
لذلك نزلوا..
That's why they came down...
لهون سكنوا..
And settled here...
مشان مواشيهم.
For the sake of their livestock.
وهذا السبب اللي بيدل على إنه أهل القرية بالأصل كانوا غنامة.
And this reason indicates that the village people were
originally sheep herders.
غنامة.
Sheep herders.
نعم.
Yes.
وأيضاً كانوا مزارعين؟
And they were also farmers?
بعدين، عند اللي الزراعة صارت إلها قيمة، بلشوا بالزراعة.
Later on, when agriculture became valuable, they started
farming.
وتطورت الزراعة عنا بهالضيعة هي خاصة.
And agriculture developed in our village specifically.
من قمح وشعير..
From wheat and barley...
ومشتقاته حمص..
And related crops like chickpeas...
وعدس.
And lentils.
بس بالأصل شو زرعوا بالجبال؟
But originally what did they plant in the mountains?
جبال، زيتون.
Mountains, olives.
زيتون؟
Olives?
زيتون.
Olives.
وفي كرمة.
And there are vines.
وفي كرمة، وهذا الزيتون هدول ما هم من زمان يعني.
And there are vines. And these olives are not from a long
time ago.
حالياً..
Currently...
بعد السبعين زرعوا.
They planted them after the seventies.
كله. بعد ما توزعت الأراضي على الفلاحين..
All the olives?
All of it. After the lands were distributed among the
farmers...
اجت نظام وزعنا على الفلاحين..
The system came and distributed to the farmers...
وبلشوا..
And they started...
رابطة الفلاحين قال ازرعوا زيتون.
The farmers' union said "Plant olives."
بلشوا كرمة وزيتون يزرعوا.
They started planting vines and olives.
طيب خليني ارجع بقى معك للسكان الأصليين في...
Okay, let me go back with you to the original inhabitants
in...
يعني الآغوات..
I mean the Aghas...
الآغوات نعم.
The Aghas, yes.
مين هنن، مين هنن؟
Who are they, who are they?
سيدي هي قديماً، عائلة الملحم.
Sir, in the past, the Al-Mulhim family.
ابنهم كانوا يقولوا له مراد آغا.
Their son was called Murad Agha.
من قرنبة.
Where are they from?
From Qarnaba.
قرنبة.
Qarnaba?
Qarnaba.
قرنبة اللي صايرة..
Qarnaba, which is located...
بعد الحدود.
Beyond the border.
بعد الحدود، نعم.
Beyond the border, yes.
وتاني عيلة إجا سكن هون..
And the second family that came to live here...
من بيت حاج عمر اللي اسمه عارف آغا.
From the Haj Omar family, named Aref Agha.
منين هو كمان؟
Where is he from as well?
من دير صوان، إجا أخد أراضي هون وسكن فيها.
From Deir Sawwan, he came and took land here and lived in
it.
نعم، يعني كانت هالضيعة إقطاعية إلن؟
Yes, so this village was a feudal estate for them?
إي نعم.
Yes, indeed.
وبعدها كمان.
During the Ottoman period?
And after that too.
نعم.
Yes.
والفلاحين كانوا يشتغلوا عندهم مرابعجية.
And the farmers used to work for them as sharecroppers.
مرابعجية، نعم.
Sharecroppers, yes.
مرابعجية. لما صارت الإصلاح الزراعي..
Sharecroppers. When the agrarian reform took place...
وتوزعت على الفلاحين القرية..
And it was distributed among the farmers of the village...
وكل واحد حط إيده على رزقه..
And everyone got their hands on their property...
وزرعوا زيتون وكرمة، وبلشوا بزراعة الحب.
And they planted olives and vines, and started planting
grains.
وفي ناس منهم، بتربية المواشي كمان لليوم.
And there are some of them, breeding livestock as well, to
this day.
لليوم؟
To this day?
لليوم.
To this day.
عندكم مواشي كتير؟
Do you have a lot of livestock?
عندنا مواشي كتير.
We have a lot of livestock.
حسب ما فهمت إنه تركيبة الضيعة، تركيبة سورية بامتياز.
From what I understood, the composition of the village is a
Syrian composition par excellence.
نعم.
Yes.
فيها كل المكونات.
It has all the components.
كل المكونات.
All the components.
احكي لي.
Tell me.
فيها أكراد.
It has Kurds.
وفيها عرب.
And it has Arabs.
وكلهم عايشين سوا.
And they all live together.
مثل الإخوة.
Like brothers.
في تركمان؟
Are there Turkmen?
تركمان ما في.
There are no Turkmen.
ما كان بالأصل فيها هون تركمان؟
Weren't there originally Turkmen here?
قديماً.
In the past.
بس رحلوا.
But they moved away.
امم.
Mmm.
العرب العشائر.
The Arab tribes.
المختار عجيلي.
The Mukhtar is Ajili.
وهالجماعة هدول بيقولوا لهم جريات.
And this group, they call them Jriyat.
وفي بيت حمادة بناوية.
And there is the Hamada Bannawiya family.
كلهم مثل الإخوة، ما في فرق.
They are all like brothers, there is no difference.
طيب والأكراد، عوائلهم؟
And the Kurds, their families?
الأكراد، العائلات اللي كانوا ساكنين هون..
The Kurds, the families that used to live here...
متل ما قال المختار، بيت سوران..
As the Mukhtar said, the Souran family...
بيت كور..
The Kour family...
بيت كريزلي..
The Krizli family...
وكمان كمان..
And also, also...
بيت بطال..
The Battal family...
بيت هريك الشيخ.
The Hrek Al-Sheikh family.
والعرب خوالهم.
And the Arabs are their maternal uncles.
وهذوليك الجماعة رحلوا كانوا ساكنين تحت كمان..
And those people moved away, they used to live down there as
well...
كانوا يقولوا لهم مسلة.
They used to call them Masla.
رحلوا هذول.
They moved away.
نعم.
Yes.
وحالياً الضيعة تطورت وكبرت، كانت كلها تلطعش بيت حالياً صارت
فوق تمانين بيت..
And currently, the village has developed and grown, it used
to be just 13 houses, now it's over 80 houses...
حوالي مية بيت.
Around 100 houses.
نعم. هلق كانت كلها بيوت طين؟
Yes. Now, were they all mud houses?
إي كلها بيوت طين وبلوك طين.
Yes, all were mud houses and mud blocks.
وبلوك طين؟
And mud blocks?
وخشب.
And wood.
سقف خشب؟
Wood roof?
سقف خشب، كانوا يحطولها عواميد، مشان ما تهبط.
Wood roof, they used to put pillars for them, so they
wouldn't collapse.
ايمتى أول بيت صار بيتون هون، يعني بأي فترة، بيتون يعني
اسمنت؟
When did the first concrete house appear here? I mean in
what period, concrete meaning cement?
أول بيتون صار..
The first concrete was...
حالياً صاير بيت استاذ حنان فوق..
Currently it's the house of Mr. Hanan up there...
أول صبة بيتون هنيكة صارت.
The first concrete pour happened there.
بأي سنة؟
In what year?
هي لازم يكون بالستينات.
It must have been in the sixties.
ستينات؟
The sixties?
إي، ما قبل كان كله بيوت طين.
Yes, before that it was all mud houses.
وبعدين شوي شوي صار الإسمنت يغزو..
And then slowly, cement started taking over...
يغزو الطين ويستبدلوه.
Taking over the mud and replacing it.
بدلوا كل شي بالاسمنت.
They replaced everything with cement.
طيب، هلق بدي اسألك..
Okay, now I want to ask you...
يعني تاريخياً كيف كانت العلاقة بين أهل الضيعة، من كل
المكونات؟
I mean historically, how was the relationship between the
people of the village, from all components?
والله على طول يعني..
Well, all the time, I mean...
متألفين ومحبوبين وكذا، إي ذاتية، شغلات بسيطة، بيحلوها.
United and beloved and such, yes internally, simple things,
they resolve them.
إي شو كانت العادات المشتركة بيناتهم؟ القيم المشتركة الحلوة
اللي بيناتهم؟ شو هي؟
Yes, what were the common traditions among them? The
beautiful common values between them? What are they?
والله كل شي كل شي حلو بالأفراح وبالأتراح.
Honestly, everything, everything is nice in times of joy and
sorrow.
كل شي ما كان في خلاف، حتى..
In everything there was no dispute, even...
حتى إذا ما بحكي مع المختار لا سمح الله، إذا مات حدا منا أو
منهم، ما بتشوف كلياتنا ع الجبانة، كلهم سوا ما في هالشيات
أبداً.
Even if I wasn't on speaking terms with the Mukhtar, God
forbid, if someone from us or them died, you'd see all of us
at the graveyard, all together, there are no such things at
all.
بدي اسألك، كان في عادة معروفة بالريف إنه أهل الضيع بيساعدوا
بعضهم في المواسم.
I want to ask you, there was a well-known custom in the
countryside that villagers help each other during the
seasons.
بالمواسم، بالكح.. حفلات، في الأتراح مثل ما قلت لك، بس حالياً
ما ضل هالشيات.
In the seasons, in the... parties, in times of sorrow as I
told you, but nowadays such things are gone.
السليقة؟
Boiling wheat (Sliqa)?
السليقة.
Sliqa.
اتذكر لي بقى السليقة هلق وطحن البرغل.
Remember for me now the Sliqa and grinding bulgur.
هي السليقة، برغل، حصادة، يحصدوا سوا..
This Sliqa, bulgur, harvesting, they harvest together...
يجنوا الزيتون سوا.
They harvest olives together.
ما كان في بالمصاري.
It wasn't with money.
يساعدوا بعضهم، فلاحين.
They helped each other, the farmers.
كلهم.
They all helped each other?
All of them.
من أرض لأرض، وحتى دراسة الجرجر والنورج.
From land to land?
From land to land, and even threshing with the Jarjar and
the Nawraj.
يلا يا جار..
Come on, neighbor...
...weled?
Come on over..
...children?
Şeş de heb reqemî ne ya Mehmûd.
It has six digits, Mahmoud.
84, maşallah. Emrê kullo.
84, mashallah. A long life!
Bi emrê kulo inşallah.
A long life, God willing.
Çend weledên te hene?
How many children do you have?
Heft, heft kur û du keç.
Seven, seven boys and two girls.
Xwedê ji te ra bihêle ya reb. Min ra qala bîranînên xwe
bike.
May God keep them for you. Tell me about your memories.
Di zemanê xweş da, gava tu hatî vir.
In the good times, when you came here.
Vir?
Here?
Wele bîranînên xweş,
Yes, good memories.
Bêjim ji te ra, ne tenê li vir.
Let me tell you, not only here.
Li herêmê hemû.
In the whole region.
Çawa? Ji min ra qala bîranîneke xweş bike.
How so? Tell me about a good memory.
Me bi ciwanî,
When we were young,
em digeriyan,
we used to wander,
em li herêmê diçûn gel hevalan, xizm û eqrebeyan.
we used to go to friends and relatives in the region.
Te dît herkes mirov dibêje qey yek mal e.
You could see everyone felt like one household.
Kesekî xerîb tune ye.
There were no strangers.
Ya selam. Ya selam.
Oh, wow. Oh, wow.
Şahî hebûn? Tiştek di dema dirûnê de?
Were there celebrations? Anything during harvest time?
Helbet.
Of course.
Ji min ra qala wan bike.
Tell me about them.
Mînak, me xwestiya ku em zeviyê biçinin.
For example, when we wanted to harvest the fields.
An dema zeytûnan an firingiyan, tiştek ji vî karî.
Or during the olive or tomato harvest, something like that.
Dirûn.
The harvest.
Ewa, pîroz dikirin, stranan digotin.
Yes, they celebrated and sang songs.
Dîlan digerandin.
They danced traditional dances (Dabkeh/Dîlan).
Ya selam.
Wow.
Bi navê xwe, dema genimê hûr dikirin, dîsa weha dikirin.
Likewise, when they ground the wheat, they did the same
thing.
Tu tiştek ji wan tiştên ku digotin an distirên dizanî? Tê
bîra te?
Do you know any of the things they used to say or sing? Do
you remember?
Ne qetek jî?
Not even a little?
Stran, ez qet nizanim.
Songs, I don't know any at all.
Ez hewesa min xwendin bû.
My passion was reading.
Xwendin?
Reading?
Min ebtîdaî (dibistana seretayî) xwend û ez pir dixwend.
I only had a primary school education, and I read a lot.
Ji min ra qala vê mijarê bike. Te çi dixwend?
Tell me about this. What did you read?
Ez difikirim, ku mirovê rojhilatî tenê bawernameyek di serê
wî da ye.
I think that the Eastern man only thinks about getting a
certificate.
Bawernameya ajotinê, eger polêsek hat, ewê jê re nîşan bide.
Like a driving license, if a policeman comes, he shows it to
him.
Lê mirovê rewşenbîr divê wek marketekê be.
But an educated person should be like a supermarket.
Mirovê rewşenbîr divê wek supermarketê be?
An educated person should be like a supermarket?
Wey li min, tê de her tişt heye.
Oh my, it has everything in it.
Her tişt.
Everything.
Te çi xwend?
What did you read?
Min, min bîranînên Anthony Eden xwend.
I... I read the memoirs of Anthony Eden.
Min xwend, Nameya Hindî-Çînî (Pirtûk).
I read the Indo-Chinese Letters (Book).
Min xwend, li ser... Boza.
I read about... Boza (Book).
Min xwend, nivîskarê Almanî Nietzsche.
I read the German writer, Nietzsche.
Erê, Nietzsche.
Yes, Nietzsche.
Wisa peyivî Zerdeşt.
Thus Spoke Zarathustra.
Pir, ji van.
Many of these.
Ji vir ve eleqeya te bi dîroka herêmê çêbû.
From here your interest in the history of the region began.
Erê, heta min dîroka Sosyalîzmê xwend.
Yes, I even read the history of Socialism.
Xwendin. Dîroka partiyên Şuyu'î di navê xwe da.
I read it. The history of the Communist parties as well.
Min her tişt xwend, min tiştek nehişt.
I read everything, I left nothing out.
Dîrok, siyaset û ol.
History, politics, and religion.
Ol, siyaset.. kîjan siyaset.
Religion, politics... what politics?
Qet siyaset tune ye.
There is no politics at all.
Anthony Eden. Bîranînên Anthony Eden. Serokwezîrê Brîtanyayê
yê berê.
Anthony Eden. The memoirs of Anthony Eden. The former
British Prime Minister.
Anthony Eden têk çû, piştî şerê li ser Kanala Suweyşê ew têk
çû.
Anthony Eden failed. He failed after the war over the Suez
Canal.
Û ew ji desthilatdariyê derxistin.
And he was removed from power.
Xwedê te xurt bike, apê Mehmûd.
May God give you strength, Uncle Mahmoud.
Xwedê we jî xurt bike, bi xêr hatin, ser çavan.
May God give you strength too, welcome, my pleasure.
Gelek spas ji te ra.
Thank you very much.
[Music playing]
Rêjeyeke baş ji niştecihên gund
A fair amount of the village's residents
ji deverên cûda yên Sûriyê koçber bûne.
are displaced people from different parts of Syria.
Wek ku hûn dibînin, kon hene
As you can see, there are tents
li başûrê rojavayê gund
in the southwest of the village,
û her weha hinek ji koçberan li malên gund dijîn.
and also some of the displaced people live in the village
houses.
Bi kirê an jî bê pere.
Either for rent or for free.
Em ê niha biçin hundirê yek ji van konan.
We are now going inside one of these tents.
Lê belê zarokên ku niha li derve dilîzin, balkêş in, tevî
hewaya sar.
But the children playing outside right now catch the eye,
despite the cold weather.
Merheba xortno, de bisekinin hûn bi çi ketine?
Hello guys, wait, what are you up to?
Ka em hinekî bi we re biaxivin.
Let's talk to you a little bit.
Hûn çawan in?
How are you?
Em baş in.
We are fine.
Navê te çi ye?
What is your name?
Feysel.
Faisal.
Bi xêr hatî Feysel.
Welcome, Faisal.
Ehmed.
Ahmed.
Bi xêr hatî.
Welcome.
Husên.
Hussein.
Bi xêr hatî.
Welcome.
Ehmed.
Ahmed.
Bi xêr hatî, bi xêr hatî.
Welcome, welcome.
Muntezer.
Muntazar.
Muntezer? Bi xêr hatî.
Muntazar? Welcome.
Xazî.
Ghazi.
Xazî? Hûn ji ku ne Muntezer?
Ghazi? Where are you from, Muntazar?
Ji Şûhe.
From Shuha.
Şûhe li ku ye?
Where is Shuha?
Li rojhilatê Seracimê.
East of Saraqib.
Ya bi xêr hatin.
Welcome.
Nexwe, hûn dilîzin? Hûn ne serma ne?
So, you're playing? Aren't you cold?
Erê, em serma ne.
Yes, we are cold.
Serma ye welleh!
It is cold, by God!
Û hûn li vir dilîzin, maşelleh.
And you are playing here, mashallah.
Hûn xwe li erdê dirêj dikin. Kî bi ser ket di lîstikê da?
You are laying down on the floor like this. Who won the
game?
Husên, Husên.
Hussein, Hussein.
Husên bi ser ket? Husên birayê te ye?
Hussein won? Is Hussein your brother?
Erê.
Yes.
Ya bi xêr hatin.
Welcome.
Ev mala kê ye?
Whose house is this?
Ya me ye.
It's ours.
Tu diçî dibistanê an ku?
Do you go to school or where?
Erê em diçin. Li dibistana wir.
Yes, we do. At the school there.
Tu her roj diçî?
Do you go every day?
Lê em di rojê panzdeh da di betlaneyê da ne.
But we are on a fifteen-day holiday.
Çima?
Why?
Nizanim.
I don't know.
Piştî dema yekem, wisa nîne?
After the first term, right?
Erê.
Yes.
Were em herin mala we.
Let's go to your house.
Ya reb, em herin.
Oh Lord, let's go.
Mala me li wir e.
Our house is over there.
Mala we li wir e? De em herin.
Your house is over there? Let's go.
[Walking]
Selamun Eleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Xwedê qewetê bide we.
May God give you strength.
Çawa ye? Mîna ku tu dicemidî?
How is it? Looks like you are freezing?
Erê welleh.
Yes, by God.
Pir an kêm?
A lot or a little?
Welleh pir e.
By God, a lot.
Hûn ji ku hatine?
Where did you come from?
Ez ji gundewarê Helebê ya başûr im.
I am from the southern countryside of Aleppo.
Bi xêr hatî, ev kon hemî yên xelkê gundewarê Helebê yên
başûr in?
Welcome, are all these tents of the people from the southern
countryside of Aleppo?
Ka em hinekî derbas bibin, bibînin.
Yes.
Let's go in and see a bit.
Silav, Xwedê quwetê bide we.
Peace, may God give you strength.
Ka ez hinekî bi we ra biaxivim. Kî eqrebeyê te ye?
Let me talk to you a little. Who is your relative?
Dêya min e.
She is my mother.
Hûn ne cemidîne?
Aren't you freezing?
Na, zêde cemidî nînin. Me sobe vêxistiye.
No, we are not freezing that much. We have lit the stove.
Hûn cemidîne, em ne cemidîne.
You are freezing, we are not freezing.
Xwedê quwetê bide we.
May God give you strength.
Xwedê quwetê bide we ya reb. Ji min re qala rewşa we li vir
bike, hûn çawa dijîn?
May God give you strength. Tell me about your situation
here, how do you live?
Welleh ez çi bibêjim te?
By God, what can I tell you?
Em di konan da rûdinin.
We live in tents.
Li malên wisa (ji pora serê xwe digire) yanî wê çawa be?
In houses of hair (tents), I mean how else would it be?
Sar, berf, sermayek giran... Û bi sitara Xwedê ye.
Cold, snow, a heavy freeze... And we are under God's
protection.
Xwedê quwetê bide we ya reb, yanî hûn dixwazin çi bikin?
May God give you strength. So, what do you want to do?
Hûn çi kar dikin? Çawa dijîn?
What kind of work do you do? How do you live?
Welleh em di nav zeviyan da dixebitin. Ew bûye pale
(Karker), em li vir û wir... Em çûn Libnanê jî ji bo em
bixebitin, lê bê feyde ye. Bê kar û bê pere ye.
By God, we work in the fields. We have become laborers, we
are here and there... We even went to Lebanon to work, but
it was useless. No work and no money.
Bi çi dixebitin?
What do you work in?
Di nav kartolan, zeytûnan, wek karker. Din tişt nîne.
In potatoes, olives, as laborers. Nothing else.
Ciwan bi çi mijûl in?
What do the young men do?
Welleh, em betal in, em bi tiştekî mijûl nînin.
By God, we are unemployed, we don't do anything.
Li vir karên weke çinîna zeytûnan nînin?
Are there no jobs here like harvesting olives?
Hebû, lê niha zeytûn tune ne.
There used to be, but now there are no olives.
Karên serbest wekî avakirin (inşaet), nîne?
Free labor like construction, is there none?
Welleh nîne.
By God, there isn't.
Welleh karên xwe nînin.
By God, there is no work.
Dema ku hûn dixwazin tiştekî bikirin, hûn ji gund dikirin an
diçin cihekî din?
When you want to buy something, do you buy from the village
or go somewhere else?
Welleh yê gund dikanin ku ji cîranan bikirin, yên ku perê
wan hene, diçin ji cihên din tînin.
By God, those in the village can buy from neighbors. Those
who have money go and get it from elsewhere.
Yanî di gund de dikan, hwd. nînin?
So there are no shops, etc. in the village?
Di gund de... Xwedê alîkariyê bike. Gund... welleh Xwedê
alîkariya wan kir. Xwedê li dinyayê û axretê başiya wan
bide.
In the village... May God help them. The village... by God,
God helped them. May God reward them in this world and the
hereafter.
Çend sal in hûn li vir in?
How many years have you been here?
Salek bûye ku em hatine.
It's been a year since we came.
Salek.
A year.
Erê.
Yes.
Ji ku hûn hatin tam?
Where did you come from exactly?
Welleh em ji Zerbeyê hatin.
By God, we came from Zerba.
Ji Zerbe bo Seharê, li ser Cewame.
From Zerba to Sahara, by Al-Jawamaa.
Gellek gund bi gund em geriyan, gundek li pey gundek, em li
vir sekinîn.
We wandered from village to village, one village after
another, and we stopped here.
Em li vir sekinîn.
We stopped here.
Ez ê pirsekî dawî ji te bikim. Bala min kişand.
I'll ask you one last question. It caught my attention.
Ev fîstanê ku te li xwe kiriye çi ye?
What is this dress you are wearing?
Ev yek, em jê re dibêjin kinc. Ji kerema xwe tu dikarî min
nîşan bidî?
This one, we call it a Thobe (dress). Could you show me,
please?
Bê guman! Ne pirsgirêk e.
Of course! Not a problem.
Ev kinc e, ev mîna li herêma we an li vir e?
This is a Thobe, is it like this in your region or here?
Na, ev herêma me ye.
No, this is our region's.
Li ku derê? Zerbeyê.
Where? Zerba.
Em rojhilatê Zerbe ne.
We are east of Zerba.
Li kû derê, tam?
Where, exactly?
Tal El-Daman.
Tal Al-Daman.
Tal El-Daman! Baş e, we re dibêjin çi? Ev, ev cilan?
Tal Al-Daman! Okay, what do you call it? This, this dress?
Em jê re dibêjin kinc, ev kinca malê.
We call it a Thobe, this is a house Thobe.
Kinca malê. Çima "Kinca Malê"?
A house Thobe. Why a "House Thobe"?
Ji ber ku wekî ku Ereb dibêjin jê re, kincên bazirganî ye.
Because as the Arabs call it, it is a commercial Thobe.
Bazirganan. Gelo yekî din heye ku jê re digotin kincekî
maqûl (Meqseb)?
Commercial. Is there another one called an elegant
(Muqassab) Thobe?
Erê, maqûl heye... ji Hevrîşimê Hindî.. hene.
Yes, there is the elegant one... made of Indian silk.. there
are.
Yanî... ev kincên ku, wek dibêjin bazirgan tên firotin.
I mean... these Thobes are, as they say, sold commercially.
Xwedê quwetê bide we.
May God give you strength.
Xwedê we jî xurt bike.
May God give you strength too.
Spas ji bo we. Xwedê xêra we binivîsîne. Xwedê we xurt bike,
baş bixebitin. Xwedê rizqê we bide.
Thank you. May God reward you. May God give you strength,
work well. May God provide for you.
[Music starts]
Yek ji taybetmendiyên herî girîng ên gund...
One of the most important landmarks of the village...
Ji bilî Geliyê Cehennemê,
Besides the Valley of Hell,
yê ku em ê di demek nêzîk da serdan bikin.
which we will visit soon.
Kaniya Gund.
The Village Spring.
Kaniya Gund ku li başûrê gund e, wek min got,
The Village Spring, which is in the south of the village, as
I said,
diherike nav robarê ku
flows into the river that
diçe benda Medankî.
goes to the Maydanki Dam.
Xelkê vir ji vê kaniyê vedixwarin.
The people here used to drink from this spring.
Û ez texmîn dikim ku heya roja îro,
And I guess that to this day,
Dibe ku ew van avan bikar tînin da ku zeviyên çandiniyê av
bidin û heta...
they might use this water to irrigate the agricultural lands
and even...
ji bo vexwarinê bikar bînin.
use it for drinking.
Em ê wê ziyaret bikin, nas bikin.
We will visit it, get to know it.
Ev kanî niha li pêşiya me ye.
This spring is now in front of us.
Weke hûn dibînin hinekî lawaz e,
As you can see, it is a bit weak,
dibe ku ji ber ku demsala baranê ya îsal kêm e.
probably because this year's rainy season is light.
Lê diyar e ku ji binî derdikeve.
But it is clear that it comes out from the bottom.
Diyar e ku ji binî derdikeve. Ev e av.
It is clear that it comes out from the bottom. This is the
water.
Diyar e ku ew ji binê vî kevirî derdikeve, an jî ji hundir
de tê.
It is clear that it comes out from under this rock, or from
inside.
Tê de hin tiştên...
It contains some...
Çiqilên hişk.
Dry branches.
Li vir xuya ye ku mirov tên û li derdora kaniyê rûdinin, avê
dadigirin, dişon.
Here it seems that people come and sit around the spring,
fill water, and wash.
Ajalên wan avê vedixwin û belkî...
Their animals drink water and maybe...
Dema ku av pir be dibe ku ew bi kar bînin ji bo ku zeviyên
xwe av bidin.
When the water is abundant, they might use it to irrigate
their lands.
Û zeviyên wan ji wê yekê av vedixwin.
And their orchards drink from it.
Helbet, li kêleka wê...
Of course, next to it...
Li aliyê rastê yê geliyê de kon hene.
On the right side of the valley there are tents.
Konên koçberan li nêzîkî kaniyê bi cih bûne.
Displaced people's tents are set up near the spring.
Ji bo ku ew (ava kaniyê) bikar bînin.
So that they can use it (the spring's water).
Bo şuştinê an vexwarinê an ji bo avdana lawiran.
For washing, drinking, or watering livestock.
Em ê niha biçin ber bi Geliyê Cehennemê. Werin bi me re.
We are now going to the Valley of Hell. Come with us.
[Music Playing]
Em ê niha biçin Geliyê Cehennemê.
We are now going to the Valley of Hell.
Geliyê Cehennemê jî li başûrê Beyyace ye.
The Valley of Hell is also in the south of Al-Bayyada.
Û Beyyace ji...
And it separates Al-Bayyada from...
gundê Ayn Eloo vediqetîne.
the village of Ayn Eloo.
[Music playing]
واضح إنه الوادي مهيب.
It is clear that the valley is majestic.
عميق جداً والهواء مرتفع، قوي.
Very deep, and the wind is high and strong.
هذا نهر عفرين، واضح، نهر عفرين بيتجه نحو ميدانكي.
This is the Afrin River, clearly. The Afrin River flows
towards Maydanki.
قرية ميدانكي اللي فيها سد، سد ميدانكي موجود.
The village of Maydanki, which has a dam, the Maydanki Dam
is there.
وهي القرية، هي هي القرية اللي واضحة ورانا، هي البياعة أو
ورقان.
And this village, the village that is visible behind us, is
Al-Bayya'a or Wergan.
رح نمشي شوي على يسار الوادي.
We will walk a little to the left of the valley.
طبعاً في خطورة إنه الإنسان يعني يفقد توازنه.
Of course, there is a danger that a person might lose their
balance.
وهو عم يمشي على سفح هذا الوادي إنه لا سمح الله يسقط.
While walking on the slope of this valley, God forbid they
might fall.
هالنبته اللي شايفينها على شكل مدرجات، آخدة شكل الوادي، هي
نبتة البلان.
This plant you see in the form of terraces, taking the shape
of the valley, is the Sarcopoterium spinosum (Bellan) plant.
طبعاً هي نبتة شوكية.
Of course, it is a thorny plant.
هذا هو الامتداد الحقيقي، أو يعني الهيكل الحقيقي لوادي جهنم.
This is the true extension, or rather, the true structure of
the Wadi Jahannam (Valley of Hell).
اللي هو امتداد من وادي، أو من مجرى نهر عفرين.
Which is an extension of the valley, or the course of the
Afrin River.
عميق.
It is deep.
هون أكيد بيكون في طيور بالصيف وبالربيع وبالخريف.
There are definitely birds here in the summer, spring, and
autumn.
بتحلق فوق هالواد وبتشرب من المي تبعو.
They fly over this valley and drink from its water.
ويمكن كمان أحياناً بتنزل وبتخيم هون.
And maybe sometimes they also come down and settle here.
رح ننزل هلا باتجاه الضيعة مرة تانية.
We will now head down towards the village once again.
هلا انتهينا من وادي جهنم، رح نرجع مرة تانية عالضيعة.
Now we are done with Wadi Jahannam, we will go back to the
village again.
رح نعمل فيها جولة بسيطة، نتعرف على حاراتها الصغيرة.
We will take a short tour there, to get to know its small
neighborhoods.
وشوارعها الضيقة، ونكمل جولتنا.
And its narrow streets, and continue our tour.
لاحظوا كيف البيوت مبنية فعلاً على سفوح هالجبل المنخفض.
Notice how the houses are actually built on the slopes of
this low mountain.
يعني المرتفع قليلاً خلينا نقول، مبنية بشكل حلو كتير كتير.
Let's say slightly elevated, they are built in a very, very
beautiful way.
ضيعة صغيرة، لكن جميلة كتير كتير.
A small village, but very, very beautiful.
الطرق وعرة كتير بهالضيعة.
The roads are very rugged in this village.
مدخل الضيعة، وهذا الجامع متل ما شايفينو.
The village entrance, and this is the mosque as you can see.
رح نتجه الآن عاليمين باتجاه المدرسة.
We will now head right towards the school.
هاي المدرسة.
This is the school.
طبعاً المدرسة ابتدائية فقط.
Of course, the school is only a primary school.
الطلاب بكملوا إما بإعزاز أو بـ... أو بشران.
The students continue their studies either in Azaz, or in...
or in Sharran.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
And upon you be peace and the mercy of God.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
نتعرف عليك؟
May we know your name?
حنان إسماعيل، مدير مدرسة ورقان.
Hanan Ismail, the principal of Wergan School.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
Welcome.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health.
هلا قبل ما اسألك على الناس هون وعلى المدرسة والتعليم.
Now, before I ask you about the people here, the school, and
the education.
هي الصخرة لفتت نظري، شو هي الصخرة؟
This rock caught my attention, what is this rock?
والله صخرة قديمة كتير، يعني بتوقع إنه صخرة بركانية.
Well, it's a very old rock, I expect it's a volcanic rock.
يعني في بقديم الزمان صاير شي بركان وفي هدول الحمم البركانية
نازلة.
I mean, in ancient times, there was a volcano, and these
volcanic lava flows came down.
ومثبتة هون بهالقرية هي.
And they settled here in this village.
وأغلب صخور هالقرية هي كلها صخور سودا بركانية.
And most of the rocks in this village are all black volcanic
rocks.
بس مو ظاهر، ما شفت شي بالقرية هيك شبهها يعني.
But it's not visible, I haven't seen anything similar in the
village.
كأنه هون لحالها يعني موجودة نافرة هيك.
It seems like it's here alone, standing out like this.
لا هي متوزعة، بس متل ما قلت لك قديمة كتير.
No, they are distributed, but as I told you, they are very
old.
فمغطاية بتراب، مغطاية بحشيش أو هيك صاير، مشان هيك.
So they are covered with dirt, covered with grass or
something like that, that's why.
تمام، يعني ممكن يكون في المنطقة هون الصخر بازلتي.
Okay, so the rocks in this area might be basaltic.
الله أعلم.
God knows best.
طيب خلينا نحكي عن المجتمع.
Alright, let's talk about the community.
احكيلي عن طبيعة الناس هون أستاذ.
Tell me about the nature of the people here, sir.
باعتبارك إنت يعني مدير مدرسة، فإنت أكيد ومن أهل الضيعة،
فأكيد إنت بتعرف شو الطبيعة.
Since you are a school principal, and you are from the
village, you definitely know what their nature is.
احكيلي عن طبيعة المجتمع.
Tell me about the nature of the community.
طبيعة المجتمع هون، الناس اللي بتشتغل هون كلها بالزراعة.
The nature of the community here, the people who work here
are all in agriculture.
وبتربية المواشي والحيوانات يعني.
And in raising livestock and animals.
التعليم ضعيف كتير هون، يعني الناس ما بتشجع ولادها.
Education is very weak here, people don't encourage their
kids.
ما بتشجع أطفالها يداوموا بالمدارس.
They don't encourage their children to attend schools.
أنا صار لي أستاذ مدرسة هون تقريباً سبع تمن سنوات.
I have been a school teacher here for about seven or eight
years.
دائماً العدد الموجود ما متناسب مع عدد الأهالي.
The number of students present is never proportional to the
number of residents.
في تقريباً 500 نسمة بالضيعة هلا.
There are about 500 people in the village right now.
الطلاب اللي بالمدرسة ما بيتعدوا الـ 100 طالب مثلاً.
The students in the school don't exceed 100 students, for
example.
المدرسة الموجودة عندي طلابها من الصف الأول للصف الخامس
الابتدائي.
The school I have has students from the first grade to the
fifth grade of primary school.
والأهالي هون أغلبهم متل ما قلت بيعتمدوا عالزراعة وعلى تربية
المواشي.
And the people here, most of them, as I said, rely on
agriculture and raising livestock.
هلا الـ 500 من النازحين وأهالي القرية ولا؟
Now, are the 500 people a mix of displaced persons and the
village residents, or?
نازحين وأهالي قرية.
Displaced persons and village residents.
أغلبهم بيعتمدوا عالفلاحة، وما في صنعة تانية يعني.
Most of them rely on farming, and there is no other
profession.
لو في صنعة تانية مثلاً، حدا عم بيروح مثلاً خارج البلد أو
خارج المدينة ليشتغل بصنعة تانية ما في.
If there were another profession, for example, someone going
outside the country or the city to work in another trade,
there isn't any.
كلهم موجودين في القرية يا إما فلاحة، يا إما زراعة.
They are all in the village, either farming or agriculture.
يا إما مع المواشي عم يبعتوا ولادهم رايحين جايين.
Or they are sending their kids back and forth with the
livestock.
احكيلي هون الزواج بأي سن بصير؟ للشباب والفتيات؟
Tell me, at what age does marriage happen here? For young
men and women?
الزواج فيه هلق زواج بسن الـ 17، 18 من العادات والتقاليد
القديمة.
Regarding marriage, there are marriages at the age of 17 or
18 due to old customs and traditions.
في عائلات بتعتمد عليها.
There are families that rely on that.
وفي عائلات متفتحة أكتر بتاخد فوق الـ 20، 22 سنة.
And there are more open-minded families that marry over the
age of 20 or 22.
حالياً 20، 22 سنة.
Currently 20, 22 years old.
تقريباً إيه.
Approximately, yes.
لسا عم بصير أعراس هون؟
Are weddings still taking place here?
في أعراس إيه، في أعراس.
Yes, there are weddings, there are weddings.
كيف بتصير؟
How do they take place?
أعراسنا هون، عادات وتقاليد هالقرية هي، أعراسها مختلطة.
Our weddings here, the customs and traditions of this
village, its weddings are mixed.
يعني عنا، أكيد عرفت إنه القرية فيها عرب وكرد مع بعض، عايشين
مع بعض.
I mean, we have, you definitely know that the village has
Arabs and Kurds together, living together.
وأعراسهم كلها مختلطة مع بعض.
And their weddings are all mixed together.
مختلطة يعني بتصير برا؟ بتصير جوا؟
Mixed meaning they happen outside? Or inside?
بالضيعة يعني مختلطة هلق في ساحة بالقرية.
In the village, meaning mixed, there is a square in the
village.
بساحة القرية بيعملوا العرس، حفل، سهرة، وهذا العرس هاد.
In the village square they hold the wedding, a party, an
evening gathering, and that's the wedding.
مختلط، وأيضاً بتشترك فيه كل المكونات.
Mixed, and also all the components participate in it.
طبعاً طبعاً، مختلط، رجال ونساء مع بعض.
Of course, of course, mixed, men and women together.
والمكونات الموجودة، التركمان والعرب والكرد، كلهم مع بعض.
And the existing components, Turkmen, Arabs, and Kurds, all
together.
طيب الشكل، العرس اللي بياخدوه شو هو؟ شكل هو عربي ولا تركماني
ولا كردي؟
Well, the style, what is the wedding style they adopt? Is it
Arab, Turkmen, or Kurdish?
فسيفساء. في أغاني كردية وفي تركماني وفي عربي.
A mosaic. There are Kurdish songs, Turkmen songs, and Arabic
songs.
بيغنوا من التلات مكونات الموجودة.
They sing from the three existing components.
حافظان شي من هالأغاني تعطيني اسمها بس، بدون ما تغنيها.
Do you memorize any of these songs to just give me their
names, without singing them?
لا من العربي ولا من الكردي ولا من التركماني.
Whether Arabic, Kurdish, or Turkmen.
هلق الأغاني، أغاني الدبكات والحفلات يعني، ماني متذكر. أغاني
شعبية.
Well, the songs, the dabke and party songs, I don't
remember. They are folk songs.
طيب أنا لفت نظري هالكوميتين الموجودين هون.
Well, these two piles here caught my attention.
وفي بكل شوارع الضيعة طرقاتها مبين هيك هدول كساحة، شو هدول؟
And they are visible in all the streets and roads of the
village as pruned branches, what are these?
هدول كساحة الدوالي، العنب، ورق العنب.
These are the pruned branches of grapevines, grapes, and
grape leaves.
بيكسحوهن، بيجيبوهن لبيوتهم، بقصقصوهن كلياتهم وبحطوهن.
They prune them, bring them to their homes, cut them all up,
and keep them.
يعني شي بيشعلوا نار للطبخ، ولتشغيل الصوبيا بالشتا.
So they can light a fire for cooking, and for operating the
heater in the winter.
تمام. الله يعطيك العافية يا أستاذ.
Great. May God give you health, sir.
الله يعافيك وأهلاً وسهلاً فيك أستاذ، تحياتي، أهلاً وسهلاً
فيك.
May God give you health and welcome, sir, my greetings,
welcome.
يا رب. السلام عليكم.
Oh God. Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
شلونك؟
How are you?
والله الحمد لله.
Well, thank God.
نتعرف عليك؟
May we know your name?
أهلين وسهلين، عادل شيخو.
Welcome, Adel Sheikho.
أهلاً وسهلاً. من أهل الضيعة؟
Welcome. Are you from the village?
من أهل الضيعة، سكان الضيعة.
From the village, a resident of the village.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك. عندك غنم كأنه، شايف عندك خواريف.
Welcome. You have sheep, it seems, I see you have lambs.
إيه في خواريف وفي الحمد لله غنم، في شي.
Yes, there are lambs and, thank God, there are sheep, we
have some.
بس ما عم نلحقلهن، عم نبيع منهن عم نصرف عليهن.
But we can't keep up with their expenses, we are selling
from them to spend on them.
طيب خلينا ندخل لجوا شوي، يا رب.
Alright, let's go inside a bit. Oh God.
شارك. هذا كله عواس؟
Let's share. Are these all Awassi sheep?
إيه كله عواس.
Yes, all are Awassi.
كله. بالمنطقة بتربى كله عواس؟
All of them. Are only Awassi sheep raised in this region?
كله عواس.
All are Awassi.
هلق أنا بعرف إنه هون بالضيعة بالذات بربوا ماعز أكتر من
الغنم.
Now, I know that here in this specific village, they raise
goats more than sheep.
في ماعز، في غنم، في مشكل.
There are goats, there are sheep, there is a mix.
في يعني في ماعز وفي غنم يعني.
There are, I mean, there are goats and there are sheep.
إنت عندك ماعز؟
Do you have goats?
ما عندي، عندي يمكن شي 10 عنزات والباقي غنمات.
I don't have many, I might have about 10 goats and the rest
are sheep.
ليش هون سمعت إنه الماعز حتى أكتر من الغنم، ليش؟
Why is it that I heard that goats are even more common than
sheep here, why?
بالجبل فيه شجرية وشغلة، الماعز عم بيعيش يحوش، مو متل الغنم.
In the mountain there are trees and things, the goats can
live by foraging, not like sheep.
الغنم بدو مصروف، بدو علف.
Sheep need expenses, they need fodder.
الغنم ما بيقدر بيعيش على حراج، بدو تبن؟
Can't sheep live on grazing land, do they need hay?
لا ما بيعيش، ما بيعيش.
No, they can't live, they can't live.
الغنم هلق بدو عزة علفه.
Sheep now need a lot of fodder.
وهلق العلف غالي، عم نبيع منه ونحط عليه.
And now fodder is expensive, we sell some of them to spend
on them.
قديه كم راس عندك؟
How many heads of sheep do you have?
في بيطلع بـ 80، 90 راس.
It comes to 80, 90 heads.
بـ 80، 90 راس. بالضيعة عموماً يعني، شقد في، في معز وغنم؟
80, 90 heads. In the village in general, how many are there,
goats and sheep?
والله الضيعة ما بحسن اعطيك عدد، يعني فيها فوق الـ 1000، 1500
راس.
By God, the village, I can't give you a number, I mean there
are over 1000, 1500 heads.
شقد نسبة الناس المعتمدين على تربية الماعز والغنم في حياتهم؟
What is the percentage of people relying on raising goats
and sheep in their lives?
والله مشكل يعني، عم يربوا معز، عم يربوا غنم مثلاً...
By God, it's mixed, some raise goats, some raise sheep for
example...
وعفواً، شقد يعني مثلاً، 20%، 30% من أهل الضيعة؟
Excuse me, how much I mean, for example, 20%, 30% of the
village people?
يعني فيها تقريباً شي 20% هيك شي، يعني هيك تقريباً.
I mean it's approximately 20% or something like that,
approximately.
معتمدين على تربية الحيوانات. في أبقار؟
Relying on animal husbandry. Are there cows?
لا أبقار ما في.
No, there are no cows.
ما في أبقار.
There are no cows.
اليوم شو وضع الثروة الحيوانية عندكم؟ هلق أنت قلت لي أنه كل
شي غالي غالي، شو الغالي احكيلي؟
Today, what is the situation of animal wealth with you? Now
you told me that everything is expensive, expensive, what is
expensive? Tell me.
والله غالي، التبن الكيلو بـ 400.
By God, it's expensive, a kilo of hay is 400.
الشعير بـ 700.
Barley is 700.
وما في مادية يعني نلحق له.
And there is no financial means to keep up with it.
عم نبيع منه، عم نروح نجيب له أكل نطعميه.
We are selling from them, going to get food to feed them.
عم ننزله عالبيزار، عم نبيع ونجيب له علف.
We are taking them to the market, selling and bringing them
fodder.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك و100 أهلاً وسهلاً، الله يسلمك أهلين أستاذ.
May God give you health and a hundred welcomes, may God keep
you safe, welcome sir.
العمة كوليزر بكر، وحدة من سيدات قرية البياعة أو وريكان.
Aunt Gulizar Bakr, one of the women of Al-Baya'a or Wrekan
village.
عمرها أكتر من 75 سنة، عندها 7 ولاد وبنات، كلهم برا سوريا.
She is over 75 years old, has 7 sons and daughters, all of
them outside Syria.
رح نزورها اليوم ببيتها المتواضع، واللي ساكن عندها أيضاً أسرة
نازحة من ريف حلب الجنوبي.
We will visit her today in her humble home, where a
displaced family from the southern countryside of Aleppo
also lives with her.
لنتعرف معها على شوي من عادات وتقاليد أهل القرية، وأيضاً رح
نتعرف معكم على أكلة من الأكلات واللي هي البورانية.
To learn with her about some of the customs and traditions
of the village people, and also we will learn with you about
one of the dishes, which is Al-Buraniyah.
أكلة مشهورة كتير بهالضيعة. تابعونا.
A very famous dish in this village. Follow us.
خالتي كوليزر.
Aunt Gulizar.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام. أهلاً وسهلاً.
And upon you be peace. Welcome.
تفضلي.
Go ahead.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
جينا لعندك. طمنيني عنك.
We came to you. Reassure me about yourself.
الحمد لله، نشكر الله.
Praise be to God, we thank God.
نمشي على رجلينا وبس، من الله.
We just walk on our feet, from God.
من الله.
From God.
قوة وصحة من الله.
Strength and health from God.
الحمد لله رب العالمين. الشباب والبنات وينهم؟
Praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds. Where are the young
men and the girls?
كل بنات، تجوزن كل مين راح ع بلاد.
All the girls got married and everyone went to a country.
والشباب؟
And the young men?
شباب بتركيا.
The young men are in Turkey.
تركيا؟
Turkey?
إنت لحالك؟
Yes.
You are alone?
لحالي جيت وضليت.
I came alone and stayed.
يلا، الله بيعين. الحجي وين؟
Well, God helps. Where is the Hajji?
الحجي الله يرحمه.
The Hajji, may God have mercy on him.
تعيشي، تعيشي. طيب، احكيلي الحياة أولاً، لما كنتي صبية، وإنت
ما زلتي صبية.
May you live long. Okay, tell me about life earlier, when
you were a young woman, and you are still a young woman.
يعني لما كنتي صغيرة، بهالضيعة أحلى ولا هلق؟
I mean when you were young, was it nicer in this village or
now?
دوم أحلى، الحمد لله.
Always nice, praise be to God.
هلق كمان أحلى، ودوم أحلى، عندي أنا عجوز...
Now it is also nicer, and it's always nice, I am an old
woman...
أنا شبعرفني، من أول من أول أحلى.
How would I know, earlier, earlier was nicer.
طيب، هلق أنا اللي سمعته واللي بعرفه، إنه أهل هالضيعة
مشهورين، وكل منطقة عفرين مشهورين في البورانية.
Okay, now what I heard and what I know is that the people of
this village are famous, and the whole Afrin region is
famous for Al-Buraniyah.
مضبوط؟ البورانية.
Right? Al-Buraniyah.
بورانية! أي بورانية، اش بعرفني بورانية.
Buraniyah! What Buraniyah, how would I know about Buraniyah.
مشان إيش هاد؟
What is this for?
شو عم تقولي؟
What are you saying?
عم أقول مشان إيش هاي البورانية، هزه هزه.
I'm saying what is this Buraniyah for, shaking, shaking.
طيب، تحكيلي يا أم إيش؟ خالتي كوليزر؟
Okay, tell me, mother of what? Aunt Gulizar?
أم أدهم.
Um Adham.
خالتي أم أدهم، احكيلي شلون بتطبخوا البورانية هون؟
Aunt Um Adham, tell me how you cook Al-Buraniyah here?
Boranî... boranî tiştek weha ye...
Buraniyah... Buraniyah is something like this...
Dew heye, em diçelqînin, em dew çêdikin û di kel dixin...
There is ayran, we shake it, we make ayran and put it to
boil...
Ta ku dikelê, nîskê dikinê, nokan dikinê...
Until it boils, we add lentils, we add chickpeas...
أول شي اللبن بنعمله عيران، وبنخلطه ع السوا.
First of all, we make the yogurt into ayran, and we mix it
well.
بعدين بنحطه ع الغاز لبين ما يغلي.
Then we put it on the stove until it boils.
بس بلش بالغليان بنحط البقوليات.
Once it starts boiling, we add the legumes.
البقوليات، عدس، العدس صاغ يعني مو عدس مجروش، والحنطة، وايش
كمان؟
Legumes, lentils, whole lentils, I mean not crushed lentils,
and wheat, and what else?
وحمص، حمص حب. تمام. بعدين؟
And chickpeas, whole chickpeas. Okay. Then?
Paşê jî xudreyê dikinê.
Afterwards, we add the vegetables.
ايمت بنحط الخضرة؟ شو هي الخضرة؟
When do we add the vegetables? What are the vegetables?
Xudre... bacanê reş...
Vegetables... black eggplants...
bacanê sor...
tomatoes...
îsotên sor.
red peppers.
الباذنجان الأسود، البندورة، وفليفلة حمرا.
Black eggplants, tomatoes, and red peppers.
تمام، هاي الخضرة الوحيدة اللي بتنحط؟ تمام.
Okay, are these the only vegetables that are added? Okay.
Tiştekî din nakinê. Berê min çêdikir, niha ez nizanim
xwarinê çêkim... ez pîr bûme.
They don't add anything else. Before I used to make it, now
I don't know how to cook... I got old.
شو عم تقولي؟
What are you saying?
عم تقول أنا كنت اطبخها قديم، هلق عن جديد ما عم نطبخ هالطبخة
يعني.
She is saying I used to cook it in the past, now recently we
don't cook this dish anymore.
إيه بس يعني شقد بتبقى ع النار؟
Yes, but I mean, how long does it stay on the fire?
شقد بتبقى ع النار؟
How long does it stay on the fire?
Heta dikeliya yavrim...
Until it boils, my dear...
Saetekê, du saetan dikeliya.
It would boil for an hour, two hours.
تقريباً ساعة ونص.
Approximately an hour and a half.
ساعة ونص، بيصيروا كلهم يعني مزيج واحد يذوبوا، ولا كيف؟
An hour and a half, do they all become, I mean, one mixture,
they melt, or how?
بيصيروا كلهم، بينطبخوا سوا؟
Do they all become, do they get cooked together?
Na helin, na helin...
They don't melt, they don't melt...
ما بيدوبوا ولكن بينطبخوا، بيصيروا أطرى ع الأكل.
They don't melt, but they are cooked, they become softer to
eat.
العدس بيصير طري للأكل، الحمص، الحنطة، والخضروات لما بنحطهم
بالمرحلة التانية، لما بينطبخوا بيبلش يبين عليه حالة الطبخ،
ساعتها بيصير جاهز للأكل.
Lentils become soft to eat, chickpeas, wheat, and the
vegetables when we add them in the second stage, when they
are cooked it starts to show signs of being cooked, then it
becomes ready to eat.
طيب، الله يعطيكي العافية خالتي كوليزر.
Okay, may God give you health, Aunt Gulizar.
Xwedê we efû bike.
May God forgive you.
شو معناه اسم كوليزر؟
What is the meaning of the name Gulizar?
Ez çi zanim, bavê min navê min kiriye.
How would I know, my father gave me my name.
بس اسم حلو!
But it's a nice name!
Na lo, ne xweş e!
No man, it is not nice!
Jineke pîr û xirabe me, nav çi xweş e!
I'm a ruined old woman, how is the name nice!
خالتي اسمك حلو كوليزر، باللغة الكردية بتعني الوردة الصفراء.
Auntie, your name is beautiful, Gulizar. In the Kurdish
language, it means the yellow rose.
الوردة الصفراء. ما شاء الله عليكي، اسم كتير حلو!
The yellow rose. Mashallah, a very beautiful name!
Na lo... Ji ku navê min xweş e?!
No man... How is my name nice?!
والله حلو.
By God, it is nice.
Welleh ne xweş e...
By God, it is not nice...
يلا، الله يعطيكي العافية.
Well, may God give you health.
Xwedê we efû bike bavê min.
May God forgive you, my dear.
شكراً إلك، شكراً إلك أستاذ أحمد.
Thank you, thank you Mr. Ahmed.
العفو، يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيك أستاذ.
You're welcome, very welcome, sir.
مع عودة قطعان الماعز والأغنام من المراعي والجرود الجبلية
المحيطة في قرية وريكان أو البياعة، تنتهي هذه الجولة الجميلة
التي استمتعنا وإياكم فيها في هذه القرية.
With the return of the flocks of goats and sheep from the
pastures and the surrounding mountainous terrain in the
village of Wrekan or Al-Baya'a, this beautiful tour, which
we enjoyed with you in this village, comes to an end.
حيث تعرفنا على معالم القرية الأساسية، وعلى تاريخها القريب
والبعيد.
Where we learned about the main landmarks of the village,
and its near and distant history.
وأيضاً استمتعنا بالتعايش الكبير بين مكوناتها الاجتماعية
المختلفة؛ العربية، والكردية، والتركمانية، التي تشكل فسيفساء
سورية متميزة.
We also enjoyed the great coexistence between its various
social components; Arab, Kurdish, and Turkmen, which form a
distinguished Syrian mosaic.
نتمنى منكم التفاعل معنا على صفحة الفيس بوك الخاصة بالقناة،
وأيضاً على معرفاتنا الظاهرة أسفل الشاشة. السلام عليكم ورحمة
الله وبركاته.
We hope you interact with us on the channel's Facebook page,
and also on our handles shown at the bottom of the screen.
Peace be upon you and the mercy of God and His blessings.